CHAPTER XVI.
AS no objection was made to the young people’s engagement with their aunt, and all Mr. Collins’s
scruples of leaving Mr. and Mrs. Bennet for a single evening during his visit were most
steadily resisted, the coach conveyed him and his five cousins at a suitable hour to
Meryton; and the girls had the pleasure of hearing, as they entered the drawing-room,
that Mr. Wickham had accepted their uncle’s invitation, and was then in the house.
When this information was given, and they had all taken their seats, Mr. Collins was
at leisure to look around him and admire, and he was so much struck with the size and
furniture of the apartment, that he declared he might almost have supposed himself in the
small summer breakfast parlour at Rosings; a comparison that did not at first convey
much gratification; but when Mrs. Philips understood from him what Rosings was, and
who was its proprietor, when she had listened to the description of only one of Lady Catherine’s
drawing-rooms, and found that the chimney-piece alone had cost eight hundred pounds, she felt
all the force of the compliment, and would hardly have resented a comparison with the
housekeeper’s room.
In describing to her all the grandeur of Lady Catherine and her mansion, with occasional
digressions in praise of his own humble abode, and the improvements it was receiving, he
was happily employed until the gentlemen joined them; and he found in Mrs. Philips a very
attentive listener, whose opinion of his consequence increased with what she heard, and who was
resolving to retail it all among her neighbours as soon as she could.
To the girls, who could not listen to their cousin, and who had nothing to do but to wish
for an instrument, and examine their own indifferent imitations of china on the mantel-piece, the
interval of waiting appeared very long.
It was over at last, however.
The gentlemen did approach: and when Mr. Wickham walked into the room, Elizabeth felt that
she had neither been seeing him before, nor thinking of him since, with the smallest degree
of unreasonable admiration.
The officers of the ——shire were in general a very creditable, gentlemanlike set and the
best of them were of the present party; but Mr, Wickham was as far beyond them all in
person, countenance, air, and walk, as they were superior to the broad-faced stuffy uncle
Philips, breathing port wine, who followed them into the room.
Mr. Wickham was the happy man towards whom almost every female eye was turned, and Elizabeth
was the happy woman by whom he finally seated himself; and the agreeable manner in which
he immediately fell into conversation, though it was only on its being a wet night, and
on the probability of a rainy season, made her feel that the commonest, dullest, most
threadbare topic might be rendered interesting by the skill of the speaker.
With such rivals for the notice of the fair as Mr. Wickham and the officers, Mr. Collins
seemed to sink into insignificance; to the young ladies he certainly was nothing; but
he had still at intervals a kind listener in Mrs. Philips, and was, by her watchfulness,
most abundantly supplied with coffee and muffin.
When the card tables were placed, he had an opportunity of obliging her, in return, by
sitting down to whist.
“I know little of the game at present,” said he, “but I shall be glad to improve
myself; for in my situation of life——” Mrs. Philips was very thankful for his compliance,
but could not wait for his reason.
Mr. Wickham did not play at whist, and with ready delight was he received at the other
table between Elizabeth and Lydia.
At first there seemed danger of Lydia’s engrossing him entirely, for she was a most
determined talker; but being likewise extremely fond of lottery tickets, she soon grew too
much interested in the game, too eager in making bets and exclaiming after prizes, to
have attention for anyone in particular.
Allowing for the common demands of the game, Mr. Wickham was therefore at leisure to talk
to Elizabeth, and she was very willing to hear him, though what she chiefly wished to
hear she could not hope to be told, the history of his acquaintance with Mr. Darcy.
She dared not even mention that gentleman.
Her curiosity, however, was unexpectedly relieved.
Mr. Wickham began the subject himself.
He inquired how far Netherfield was from Meryton; and, after receiving her answer, asked in
a hesitating manner how long Mr. Darcy had been staying there.
“About a month,” said Elizabeth; and then, unwilling to let the subject drop, added,
“he is a man of very large property in Derbyshire, I understand.”
“Yes,” replied Wickham; “his estate there is a noble one.
A clear ten thousand per annum.
You could not have met with a person more capable of giving you certain information
on that head than myself—for I have been connected with his family, in a particular
manner, from my infancy.”
Elizabeth could not but look surprised.
“You may well be surprised, Miss Bennet, at such an assertion, after seeing, as you
probably might, the very cold manner of our meeting yesterday.
Are you much acquainted with Mr. Darcy?”
“As much as I ever wish to be,” cried Elizabeth, warmly.
“I have spent four days in the same house with him, and I think him very disagreeable.”
“I have no right to give my opinion,” said Wickham, “as to his being agreeable
or otherwise.
I am not qualified to form one.
I have known him too long and too well to be a fair judge.
It is impossible for me to be impartial.
But I believe your opinion of him would in general astonish—and, perhaps, you would
not express it quite so strongly anywhere else.
Here you are in your own family.”
“Upon my word I say no more here than I might say in any house in the neighbourhood,
except Netherfield.
He is not at all liked in Hertfordshire.
Everybody is disgusted with his pride.
You will not find him more favourably spoken of by anyone.”
“I cannot pretend to be sorry,” said Wickham, after a short interruption, “that he or
that any man should not be estimated beyond their deserts; but with him I believe it does
not often happen.
The world is blinded by his fortune and consequence, or frightened by his high and imposing manners,
and sees him only as he chooses to be seen.”
“I should take him, even on my slight acquaintance, to be an ill-tempered man.”
Wickham only shook his head.
“I wonder,” said he, at the next opportunity of speaking, “whether he is likely to be
in this country much longer.”
“I do not at all know; but I heard nothing of his going away when I was at Netherfield.
I hope your plans in favour of the ——shire will not be affected by his being in the neighbourhood.”
“Oh no—it is not for me to be driven away by Mr. Darcy.
If he wishes to avoid seeing me he must go.
We are not on friendly terms, and it always gives me pain to meet him, but I have no reason
for avoiding him but what I might proclaim to all the world—a sense of very great ill-usage,
and most painful regrets at his being what he is.
His father, Miss Bennet, the late Mr. Darcy, was one of the best men that ever breathed,
and the truest friend I ever had; and I can never be in company with this Mr. Darcy without
being grieved to the soul by a thousand tender recollections.
His behaviour to myself has been scandalous; but I verily believe I could forgive him anything
and everything, rather than his disappointing the hopes and disgracing the memory of his
father.”
Elizabeth found the interest of the subject increase, and listened with all her heart;
but the delicacy of it prevented further inquiry.
Mr. Wickham began to speak on more general topics, Meryton, the neighbourhood, the society,
appearing highly pleased with all that he had yet seen, and speaking of the latter,
especially, with gentle but very intelligible gallantry.
“It was the prospect of constant society, and good society,” he added, “which was
my chief inducement to enter the ——shire.
I know it to be a most respectable, agreeable corps; and my friend Denny tempted me further
by his account of their present quarters, and the very great attentions and excellent
acquaintance Meryton had procured them.
Society, I own, is necessary to me.
I have been a disappointed man, and my spirits will not bear solitude.
I must have employment and society.
A military life is not what I was intended for, but circumstances have now made it eligible.
The church ought to have been my profession—I was brought up for the church; and I should
at this time have been in possession of a most valuable living, had it pleased the gentleman
we were speaking of just now.”
“Indeed!”
“Yes—the late Mr. Darcy bequeathed me the next presentation of the best living in
his gift.
He was my godfather, and excessively attached to me.
I cannot do justice to his kindness.
He meant to provide for me amply, and thought he had done it; but when the living fell,
it was given elsewhere.”
“Good heavens!”
cried Elizabeth; “but how could that be?
How could his will be disregarded?
Why did not you seek legal redress?”
“There was just such an informality in the terms of the bequest as to give me no hope
from law.
A man of honour could not have doubted the intention, but Mr. Darcy chose to doubt it—or
to treat it as a merely conditional recommendation, and to assert that I had forfeited all claim
to it by extravagance, imprudence, in short, anything or nothing.
Certain it is that the living became vacant two years ago, exactly as I was of an age
to hold it, and that it was given to another man; and no less certain is it, that I cannot
accuse myself of having really done anything to deserve to lose it.
I have a warm unguarded temper, and I may perhaps have sometimes spoken my opinion of
him, and to him, too freely.
I can recall nothing worse.
But the fact is, that we are very different sort of men, and that he hates me.”
“This is quite shocking!
He deserves to be publicly disgraced.”
“Some time or other he will be—but it shall not be by me.
Till I can forget his father, I can never defy or expose him.”
Elizabeth honoured him for such feelings, and thought him handsomer than ever as he
expressed them.
“But what,” said she, after a pause, “can have been his motive?
what can have induced him to behave so cruelly?”
“A thorough, determined dislike of me—a dislike which I cannot but attribute in some
measure to jealousy.
Had the late Mr. Darcy liked me less, his son might have borne with me better; but his
father’s uncommon attachment to me irritated him, I believe, very early in life.
He had not a temper to bear the sort of competition in which we stood—the sort of preference
which was often given me.”
“I had not thought Mr. Darcy so bad as this—though I have never liked him, I had not thought
so very ill of him—I had supposed him to be despising his fellow-creatures in general,
but did not suspect him of descending to such malicious revenge, such injustice, such inhumanity
as this!”
After a few minutes’ reflection, however, she continued, “I do remember his boasting
one day, at Netherfield, of the implacability of his resentments, of his having an unforgiving
temper.
His disposition must be dreadful.”
“I will not trust myself on the subject,” replied Wickham; “I can hardly be just to
him.”
Elizabeth was again deep in thought, and after a time exclaimed, “To treat in such a manner
the godson, the friend, the favourite of his father!”
She could have added, “A young man, too, like you, whose very countenance may vouch
for your being amiable.”
But she contented herself with—“And one, too, who had probably been his own companion
from childhood, connected together, as I think you said, in the closest manner.”
“We were born in the same parish, within the same park; the greatest part of our youth
was passed together: inmates of the same house, sharing the same amusements, objects of the
same parental care.
My father began life in the profession which your uncle, Mr. Philips, appears to do so
much credit to; but he gave up everything to be of use to the late Mr. Darcy, and devoted
all his time to the care of the Pemberley property.
He was most highly esteemed by Mr. Darcy, a most intimate, confidential friend.
Mr. Darcy often acknowledged himself to be under the greatest obligations to my father’s
active superintendence; and when, immediately before my father’s death, Mr. Darcy gave
him a voluntary promise of providing for me, I am convinced that he felt it to be as much
a debt of gratitude to him as of affection to myself.”
“How strange!”
cried Elizabeth.
“How abominable!
I wonder that the very pride of this Mr. Darcy has not made him just to you.
If from no better motive, that he should not have been too proud to be dishonest,—for
dishonesty I must call it.”
“It is wonderful,” replied Wickham; “for almost all his actions may be traced to pride;
and pride has often been his best friend.
It has connected him nearer with virtue than any other feeling.
But we are none of us consistent; and in his behaviour to me there were stronger impulses
even than pride.”
“Can such abominable pride as his have ever done him good?”
“Yes; it has often led him to be liberal and generous; to give his money freely, to
display hospitality, to assist his tenants, and relieve the poor.
Family pride, and filial pride, for he is very proud of what his father was, have done
this.
Not to appear to disgrace his family, to degenerate from the popular qualities, or lose the influence
of the Pemberley House, is a powerful motive.
He has also brotherly pride, which, with some brotherly affection, makes him a very kind
and careful guardian of his sister; and you will hear him generally cried up as the most
attentive and best of brothers.”
“What sort of a girl is Miss Darcy?”
He shook his head.
“I wish I could call her amiable.
It gives me pain to speak ill of a Darcy; but she is too much like her brother,—very,
very proud.
As a child, she was affectionate and pleasing, and extremely fond of me; and I have devoted
hours and hours to her amusement.
But she is nothing to me now.
She is a handsome girl, about fifteen or sixteen, and, I understand, highly accomplished.
Since her father’s death her home has been London, where a lady lives with her, and superintends
her education.”
After many pauses and many trials of other subjects, Elizabeth could not help reverting
once more to the first, and saying,— “I am astonished at his intimacy with Mr.
Bingley.
How can Mr. Bingley, who seems good-humour itself, and is, I really believe, truly amiable,
be in friendship with such a man?
How can they suit each other?
Do you know Mr. Bingley?”
“Not at all.”
“He is a sweet-tempered, amiable, charming man.
He cannot know what Mr. Darcy is.”
“Probably not; but Mr. Darcy can please where he chooses.
He does not want abilities.
He can be a conversible companion if he thinks it worth his while.
Among those who are at all his equals in consequence, he is a very different man from what he is
to the less prosperous.
His pride never deserts him; but with the rich he is liberal-minded, just, sincere,
rational, honourable, and, perhaps, agreeable,—allowing something for fortune and figure.”
The whist party soon afterwards breaking up, the players gathered round the other table,
and Mr. Collins took his station between his cousin Elizabeth and Mrs. Philips.
The usual inquiries as to his success were made by the latter.
It had not been very great; he had lost every point; but when Mrs. Philips began to express
her concern thereupon, he assured her, with much earnest gravity, that it was not of the
least importance; that he considered the money as a mere trifle, and begged she would not
make herself uneasy.
“I know very well, madam,” said he, “that when persons sit down to a card table they
must take their chance of these things,—and happily I am not in such circumstances as
to make five shillings any object.
There are, undoubtedly, many who could not say the same; but, thanks to Lady Catherine
de Bourgh, I am removed far beyond the necessity of regarding little matters.”
Mr. Wickham’s attention was caught; and after observing Mr. Collins for a few moments,
he asked Elizabeth in a low voice whether her relations were very intimately acquainted
with the family of De Bourgh.
“Lady Catherine de Bourgh,” she replied, “has very lately given him a living.
I hardly know how Mr. Collins was first introduced to her notice, but he certainly has not known
her long.”
“You know of course that Lady Catherine de Bourgh and Lady Anne Darcy were sisters;
consequently that she is aunt to the present Mr. Darcy.”
“No, indeed, I did not.
I knew nothing at all of Lady Catherine’s connections.
I never heard of her existence till the day before yesterday.”
“Her daughter, Miss de Bourgh, will have a very large fortune, and it is believed that
she and her cousin will unite the two estates.”
This information made Elizabeth smile, as she thought of poor Miss Bingley.
Vain indeed must be all her attentions, vain and useless her affection for his sister and
her praise of himself, if he were already self-destined to another.
“Mr. Collins,” said she, “speaks highly both of Lady Catherine and her daughter; but,
from some particulars that he has related of her Ladyship, I suspect his gratitude misleads
him; and that, in spite of her being his patroness, she is an arrogant, conceited woman.”
“I believe her to be both in a great degree,” replied Wickham; “I have not seen her for
many years; but I very well remember that I never liked her, and that her manners were
dictatorial and insolent.
She has the reputation of being remarkably sensible and clever; but I rather believe
she derives part of her abilities from her rank and fortune, part from her authoritative
manner, and the rest from the pride of her nephew, who chooses that everyone connected
with him should have an understanding of the first class.”
Elizabeth allowed that he had given a very rational account of it, and they continued
talking together with mutual satisfaction till supper put an end to cards, and gave
the rest of the ladies their share of Mr. Wickham’s attentions.
There could be no conversation in the noise of Mrs. Philips’s supper party, but his
manners recommended him to everybody.
Whatever he said, was said well; and whatever he did, done gracefully.
Elizabeth went away with her head full of him.
She could think of nothing but of Mr. Wickham, and of what he had told her, all the way home;
but there was not time for her even to mention his name as they went, for neither Lydia nor
Mr. Collins were once silent.
Lydia talked incessantly of lottery tickets, of the fish she had lost and the fish she
had won; and Mr. Collins, in describing the civility of Mr. and Mrs. Philips, protesting
that he did not in the least regard his losses at whist, enumerating all the dishes at supper,
and repeatedly fearing that he crowded his cousins, had more to say than he could well
manage before the carriage stopped at Longbourn House.
delighted to see their dear friend again.
CHAPTER XVII.
ELIZABETH related to Jane, the next day, what had passed between Mr. Wickham and herself.
Jane listened with astonishment and concern: she knew not how to believe that Mr. Darcy
could be so unworthy of Mr. Bingley’s regard; and yet it was not in her nature to question
the veracity of a young man of such amiable appearance as Wickham.
The possibility of his having really endured such unkindness was enough to interest all
her tender feelings; and nothing therefore remained to be done but to think well of them
both, to defend the conduct of each, and throw into the account of accident or mistake whatever
could not be otherwise explained.
“They have both,” said she, “been deceived, I dare say, in some way or other, of which
we can form no idea.
Interested people have perhaps misrepresented each to the other.
It is, in short, impossible for us to conjecture the causes or circumstances which may have
alienated them, without actual blame on either side.”
“Very true, indeed; and now, my dear Jane, what have you got to say in behalf of the
interested people who have probably been concerned in the business?
Do clear them, too, or we shall be obliged to think ill of somebody.”
“Laugh as much as you choose, but you will not laugh me out of my opinion.
My dearest Lizzy, do but consider in what a disgraceful light it places Mr. Darcy, to
be treating his father’s favourite in such a manner,—one whom his father had promised
to provide for.
It is impossible.
No man of common humanity, no man who had any value for his character, could be capable
of it.
Can his most intimate friends be so excessively deceived in him?
Oh no.”
“I can much more easily believe Mr. Bingley’s being imposed on than that Mr. Wickham should
invent such a history of himself as he gave me last night; names, facts, everything mentioned
without ceremony.
If it be not so, let Mr. Darcy contradict it.
Besides, there was truth in his looks.”
“It is difficult, indeed—it is distressing.
One does not know what to think.”
“I beg your pardon;—one knows exactly what to think.”
But Jane could think with certainty on only one point,—that Mr. Bingley, if he had been
imposed on, would have much to suffer when the affair became public.
The two young ladies were summoned from the shrubbery, where this conversation passed,
by the arrival of some of the very persons of whom they had been speaking; Mr. Bingley
and his sisters came to give their personal invitation for the long expected ball at Netherfield,
which was fixed for the following Tuesday.
The two ladies were delighted to see their dear friend again, called it an age since
they had met, and repeatedly asked what she had been doing with herself since their separation.
To the rest of the family they paid little attention; avoiding Mrs. Bennet as much as
possible, saying not much to Elizabeth, and nothing at all to the others.
They were soon gone again, rising from their seats with an activity which took their brother
by surprise, and hurrying off as if eager to escape from Mrs. Bennet’s civilities.
The prospect of the Netherfield ball was extremely agreeable to every female of the family.
Mrs. Bennet chose to consider it as given in compliment to her eldest daughter, and
was particularly flattered by receiving the invitation from Mr. Bingley himself, instead
of a ceremonious card.
Jane pictured to herself a happy evening in the society of her two friends, and the attentions
of their brother; and Elizabeth thought with pleasure of dancing a great deal with Mr.
Wickham, and of seeing a confirmation of everything in Mr. Darcy’s look and behaviour.
The happiness anticipated by Catherine and Lydia depended less on any single event, or
any particular person; for though they each, like Elizabeth, meant to dance half the evening
with Mr. Wickham, he was by no means the only partner who could satisfy them, and a ball
was, at any rate, a ball.
And even Mary could assure her family that she had no disinclination for it.
“While I can have my mornings to myself,” said she, “it is enough.
I think it is no sacrifice to join occasionally in evening engagements.
Society has claims on us all; and I profess myself one of those who consider intervals
of recreation and amusement as desirable for everybody.”
Elizabeth’s spirits were so high on the occasion, that though she did not often speak
unnecessarily to Mr. Collins, she could not help asking him whether he intended to accept
Mr. Bingley’s invitation, and if he did, whether he would think it proper to join in
the evening’s amusement; and she was rather surprised to find that he entertained no scruple
whatever on that head, and was very far from dreading a rebuke, either from the Archbishop
or Lady Catherine de Bourgh, by venturing to dance.
“I am by no means of opinion, I assure you,” said he, “that a ball of this kind, given
by a young man of character, to respectable people, can have any evil tendency; and I
am so far from objecting to dancing myself, that I shall hope to be honoured with the
hands of all my fair cousins in the course of the evening; and I take this opportunity
of soliciting yours, Miss Elizabeth, for the two first dances especially; a preference
which I trust my cousin Jane will attribute to the right cause, and not to any disrespect
for her.”
Elizabeth felt herself completely taken in.
She had fully proposed being engaged by Wickham for those very dances; and to have Mr. Collins
instead!—her liveliness had been never worse timed.
There was no help for it, however.
Mr. Wickham’s happiness and her own was perforce delayed a little longer, and Mr.
Collins’s proposal accepted with as good a grace as she could.
She was not the better pleased with his gallantry, from the idea it suggested of something more.
It now first struck her, that she was selected from among her sisters as worthy of being
the mistress of Hunsford Parsonage, and of assisting to form a quadrille table at Rosings,
in the absence of more eligible visitors.
The idea soon reached to conviction, as she observed his increasing civilities towards
herself, and heard his frequent attempt at a compliment on her wit and vivacity; and
though more astonished than gratified herself by this effect of her charms, it was not long
before her mother gave her to understand that the probability of their marriage was exceedingly
agreeable to her.
Elizabeth, however, did not choose to take the hint, being well aware that a serious
dispute must be the consequence of any reply.
Mr. Collins might never make the offer, and, till he did, it was useless to quarrel about
him.
If there had not been a Netherfield ball to prepare for and talk of, the younger Miss
Bennets would have been in a pitiable state at this time; for, from the day of the invitation
to the day of the ball, there was such a succession of rain as prevented their walking to Meryton
once.
No aunt, no officers, no news could be sought after; the very shoe-roses for Netherfield
were got by proxy.
Even Elizabeth might have found some trial of her patience in weather which totally suspended
the improvement of her acquaintance with Mr. Wickham; and nothing less than a dance on
Tuesday could have made such a Friday, Saturday, Sunday, and Monday endurable to Kitty and
Lydia.
CHAPTER XVIII.
TILL Elizabeth entered the drawing-room at Netherfield, and looked in vain for Mr. Wickham
among the cluster of red coats there assembled, a doubt of his being present had never occurred
to her.
The certainty of meeting him had not been checked by any of those recollections that
might not unreasonably have alarmed her.
She had dressed with more than usual care, and prepared in the highest spirits for the
conquest of all that remained unsubdued of his heart, trusting that it was not more than
might be won in the course of the evening.
But in an instant arose the dreadful suspicion of his being purposely omitted, for Mr. Darcy’s
pleasure, in the Bingleys’ invitation to the officers; and though this was not exactly
the case, the absolute fact of his absence was pronounced by his friend Mr. Denny, to
whom Lydia eagerly applied, and who told them that Wickham had been obliged to go to town
on business the day before, and was not yet returned; adding, with a significant smile,—
“I do not imagine his business would have called him away just now, if he had not wished
to avoid a certain gentleman here.”
This part of his intelligence, though unheard by Lydia, was caught by Elizabeth; and, as
it assured her that Darcy was not less answerable for Wickham’s absence than if her first
surmise had been just, every feeling of displeasure against the former was so sharpened by immediate
disappointment, that she could hardly reply with tolerable civility to the polite inquiries
which he directly afterwards approached to make.
Attention, forbearance, patience with Darcy, was injury to Wickham.
She was resolved against any sort of conversation with him, and turned away with a degree of
ill-humour which she could not wholly surmount even in speaking to Mr. Bingley, whose blind
partiality provoked her.
But Elizabeth was not formed for ill-humour; and though every prospect of her own was destroyed
for the evening, it could not dwell long on her spirits; and, having told all her griefs
to Charlotte Lucas, whom she had not seen for a week, she was soon able to make a voluntary
transition to the oddities of her cousin, and to point him out to her particular notice.
The two first dances, however, brought a return of distress: they were dances of mortification.
Mr. Collins, awkward and solemn, apologizing instead of attending, and often moving wrong
without being aware of it, gave her all the shame and misery which a disagreeable partner
for a couple of dances can give.
The moment of her release from him was ecstasy.
She danced next with an officer, and had the refreshment of talking of Wickham, and of
hearing that he was universally liked.
When those dances were over, she returned to Charlotte Lucas, and was in conversation
with her, when she found herself suddenly addressed by Mr. Darcy, who took her so much
by surprise in his application for her hand, that, without knowing what she did, she accepted
him.
He walked away again immediately, and she was left to fret over her own want of presence
of mind: Charlotte tried to console her.
“I dare say you will find him very agreeable.”
“Heaven forbid!
That would be the greatest misfortune of all!
To find a man agreeable whom one is determined to hate!
Do not wish me such an evil.”
When the dancing recommenced, however, and Darcy approached to claim her hand, Charlotte
could not help cautioning her, in a whisper, not to be a simpleton, and allow her fancy
for Wickham to make her appear unpleasant in the eyes of a man often times his consequence.
Elizabeth made no answer, and took her place in the set, amazed at the dignity to which
she was arrived in being allowed to stand opposite to Mr. Darcy, and reading in her
neighbours’ looks their equal amazement in beholding it.
They stood for some time without speaking a word; and she began to imagine that their
silence was to last through the two dances, and, at first, was resolved not to break it;
till suddenly fancying that it would be the greater punishment to her partner to oblige
him to talk, she made some slight observation on the dance.
He replied, and was again silent.
After a pause of some minutes, she addressed him a second time, with—
“It is your turn to say something now, Mr. Darcy.
I talked about the dance, and you ought to make some kind of remark on the size of the
room, or the number of couples.”
He smiled, and assured her that whatever she wished him to say should be said.
“Very well; that reply will do for the present.
Perhaps, by-and-by, I may observe that private balls are much pleasanter than public ones;
but now we may be silent.”
“Do you talk by rule, then, while you are dancing?”
“Sometimes.
One must speak a little, you know.
It would look odd to be entirely silent for half an hour together; and yet, for the advantage
of some, conversation ought to be so arranged as that they may have the trouble of saying
as little as possible.”
“Are you consulting your own feelings in the present case, or do you imagine that you
are gratifying mine?”
“Both,” replied Elizabeth archly; “for I have always seen a great similarity in the
turn of our minds.
We are each of an unsocial, taciturn disposition, unwilling to speak, unless we expect to say
something that will amaze the whole room, and be handed down to posterity with all the
éclat of a proverb.”
“This is no very striking resemblance of your own character, I am sure,” said he.
“How near it may be to mine, I cannot pretend to say.
You think it a faithful portrait, undoubtedly.”
“I must not decide on my own performance.”
He made no answer; and they were again silent till they had gone down the dance, when he
asked her if she and her sisters did not very often walk to Meryton.
She answered in the affirmative; and, unable to resist the temptation, added, “When you
met us there the other day, we had just been forming a new acquaintance.”
The effect was immediate.
A deeper shade of hauteur overspread his features, but he said not a word; and Elizabeth, though
blaming herself for her own weakness, could not go on.
At length Darcy spoke, and in a constrained manner said,—
“Mr. Wickham is blessed with such happy manners as may insure his making friends;
whether he may be equally capable of retaining them, is less certain.”
“He has been so unlucky as to lose your friendship,” replied Elizabeth, with emphasis,
“and in a manner which he is likely to suffer from all his life.”
Darcy made no answer, and seemed desirous of changing the subject.
At that moment Sir William Lucas appeared close to them, meaning to pass through the
set to the other side of the room; but, on perceiving Mr. Darcy, he stopped, with a bow
of superior courtesy, to compliment him on his dancing and his partner.
“I have been most highly gratified, indeed, my dear sir; such very superior dancing is
not often seen.
It is evident that you belong to the first circles.
Allow me to say, however, that your fair partner does not disgrace you: and that I must hope
to have this pleasure often repeated, especially when a certain desirable event, my dear Miss
Eliza (glancing at her sister and Bingley), shall take place.
What congratulations will then flow in!
I appeal to Mr. Darcy;—but let me not interrupt you, sir.
You will not thank me for detaining you from the bewitching converse of that young lady,
whose bright eyes are also upbraiding me.”
“Such very superior dancing is not often seen.”
The latter part of this address was scarcely heard by Darcy; but Sir William’s allusion
to his friend seemed to strike him forcibly, and his eyes were directed, with a very serious
expression, towards Bingley and Jane, who were dancing together.
Recovering himself, however, shortly, he turned to his partner, and said,—
“Sir William’s interruption has made me forget what we were talking of.”
“I do not think we were speaking at all.
Sir William could not have interrupted any two people in the room who had less to say
for themselves.
We have tried two or three subjects already without success, and what we are to talk of
next I cannot imagine.”
“What think you of books?” said he, smiling.
“Books—oh no!—I am sure we never read the same, or not with the same feelings.”
“I am sorry you think so; but if that be the case, there can at least be no want of
subject.
We may compare our different opinions.”
“No—I cannot talk of books in a ball-room; my head is always full of something else.”
“The present always occupies you in such scenes—does it?” said he, with a look
of doubt.
“Yes, always,” she replied, without knowing what she said; for her thoughts had wandered
far from the subject, as soon afterwards appeared by her suddenly exclaiming, “I remember
hearing you once say, Mr. Darcy, that you hardly ever forgave;—that your resentment,
once created, was unappeasable.
You are very cautious, I suppose, as to its being created?”
“I am,” said he, with a firm voice.
“And never allow yourself to be blinded by prejudice?”
“I hope not.”
“It is particularly incumbent on those who never change their opinion, to be secure of
judging properly at first.”
“May I ask to what these questions tend?”
“Merely to the illustration of your character,” said she, endeavouring to shake off her gravity.
“I am trying to make it out.”
“And what is your success?”
She shook her head.
“I do not get on at all.
I hear such different accounts of you as puzzle me exceedingly.”
“I can readily believe,” answered he, gravely, “that reports may vary greatly
with respect to me; and I could wish, Miss Bennet, that you were not to sketch my character
at the present moment, as there is reason to fear that the performance would reflect
no credit on either.”
“But if I do not take your likeness now, I may never have another opportunity.”
“I would by no means suspend any pleasure of yours,” he coldly replied.
She said no more, and they went down the other dance and parted in silence; on each side
dissatisfied, though not to an equal degree; for in Darcy’s breast there was a tolerably
powerful feeling towards her, which soon procured her pardon, and directed all his anger against
another.
They had not long separated when Miss Bingley came towards her, and, with an expression
of civil disdain, thus accosted her,— “So, Miss Eliza, I hear you are quite delighted
with George Wickham?
Your sister has been talking to me about him, and asking me a thousand questions; and I
find that the young man forgot to tell you, among his other communications, that he was
the son of old Wickham, the late Mr. Darcy’s steward.
Let me recommend you, however, as a friend, not to give implicit confidence to all his
assertions; for, as to Mr. Darcy’s using him ill, it is perfectly false: for, on the
contrary, he has been always remarkably kind to him, though George Wickham has treated
Mr. Darcy in a most infamous manner.
I do not know the particulars, but I know very well that Mr. Darcy is not in the least
to blame; that he cannot bear to hear George Wickham mentioned; and that though my brother
thought he could not well avoid including him in his invitation to the officers, he
was excessively glad to find that he had taken himself out of the way.
His coming into the country at all is a most insolent thing, indeed, and I wonder how he
could presume to do it.
I pity you, Miss Eliza, for this discovery of your favourite’s guilt; but really, considering
his descent, one could not expect much better.”
“His guilt and his descent appear, by your account, to be the same,” said Elizabeth,
angrily; “for I have heard you accuse him of nothing worse than of being the son of
Mr. Darcy’s steward, and of that, I can assure you, he informed me himself.”
“I beg your pardon,” replied Miss Bingley, turning away with a sneer.
“Excuse my interference; it was kindly meant.”
“Insolent girl!” said Elizabeth to herself.
“You are much mistaken if you expect to influence me by such a paltry attack as this.
I see nothing in it but your own wilful ignorance and the malice of Mr. Darcy.”
She then sought her eldest sister, who had undertaken to make inquiries on the same subject
of Bingley.
Jane met her with a smile of such sweet complacency, a glow of such happy expression, as sufficiently
marked how well she was satisfied with the occurrences of the evening.
Elizabeth instantly read her feelings; and, at that moment, solicitude for Wickham, resentment
against his enemies, and everything else, gave way before the hope of Jane’s being
in the fairest way for happiness.
“I want to know,” said she, with a countenance no less smiling than her sister’s, “what
you have learnt about Mr. Wickham.
But perhaps you have been too pleasantly engaged to think of any third person, in which case
you may be sure of my pardon.”
“No,” replied Jane, “I have not forgotten him; but I have nothing satisfactory to tell
you.
Mr. Bingley does not know the whole of his history, and is quite ignorant of the circumstances
which have principally offended Mr. Darcy; but he will vouch for the good conduct, the
probity and honour, of his friend, and is perfectly convinced that Mr. Wickham has deserved
much less attention from Mr. Darcy than he has received; and I am sorry to say that by
his account, as well as his sister’s, Mr. Wickham is by no means a respectable young
man.
I am afraid he has been very imprudent, and has deserved to lose Mr. Darcy’s regard.”
“Mr. Bingley does not know Mr. Wickham himself.”
“No; he never saw him till the other morning at Meryton.”
“This account then is what he has received from Mr. Darcy.
I am perfectly satisfied.
But what does he say of the living?”
“He does not exactly recollect the circumstances, though he has heard them from Mr. Darcy more
than once, but he believes that it was left to him conditionally only.”
“I have not a doubt of Mr. Bingley’s sincerity,” said Elizabeth warmly, “but you must excuse
my not being convinced by assurances only.
Mr. Bingley’s defence of his friend was a very able one, I dare say; but since he
is unacquainted with several parts of the story, and has learnt the rest from that friend
himself, I shall venture still to think of both gentlemen as I did before.”
She then changed the discourse to one more gratifying to each, and on which there could
be no difference of sentiment.
Elizabeth listened with delight to the happy though modest hopes which Jane entertained
of Bingley’s regard, and said all in her power to heighten her confidence in it.
On their being joined by Mr. Bingley himself, Elizabeth withdrew to Miss Lucas; to whose
inquiry after the pleasantness of her last partner she had scarcely replied, before Mr.
Collins came up to them, and told her with great exultation, that he had just been so
fortunate as to make a most important discovery.
“I have found out,” said he, “by a singular accident, that there is now in the room a
near relation to my patroness.
I happened to overhear the gentleman himself mentioning to the young lady who does the
honours of this house the names of his cousin Miss De Bourgh, and of her mother, Lady Catherine.
How wonderfully these sort of things occur!
Who would have thought of my meeting with—perhaps—a nephew of Lady Catherine de Bourgh in this
assembly!
I am most thankful that the discovery is made in time for me to pay my respects to him,
which I am now going to do, and trust he will excuse my not having done it before.
My total ignorance of the connection must plead my apology.”
“You are not going to introduce yourself to Mr. Darcy?”
“Indeed I am.
I shall entreat his pardon for not having done it earlier.
I believe him to be Lady Catherine’s nephew.
It will be in my power to assure him that her Ladyship was quite well yesterday se’nnight.”
Elizabeth tried hard to dissuade him from such a scheme; assuring him that Mr. Darcy
would consider his addressing him without introduction as an impertinent freedom, rather
than a compliment to his aunt; that it was not in the least necessary there should be
any notice on either side, and that if it were, it must belong to Mr. Darcy, the superior
in consequence, to begin the acquaintance.
Mr. Collins listened to her with the determined air of following his own inclination, and
when she ceased speaking, replied thus,— “My dear Miss Elizabeth, I have the highest
opinion in the world of your excellent judgment in all matters within the scope of your understanding,
but permit me to say that there must be a wide difference between the established forms
of ceremony amongst the laity and those which regulate the clergy; for, give me leave to
observe that I consider the clerical office as equal in point of dignity with the highest
rank in the kingdom—provided that a proper humility of behaviour is at the same time
maintained.
You must, therefore, allow me to follow the dictates of my conscience on this occasion,
which lead me to perform what I look on as a point of duty.
Pardon me for neglecting to profit by your advice, which on every other subject shall
be my constant guide, though in the case before us I consider myself more fitted by education
and habitual study to decide on what is right than a young lady like yourself;” and with
a low bow he left her to attack Mr. Darcy, whose reception of his advances she eagerly
watched, and whose astonishment at being so addressed was very evident.
Her cousin prefaced his speech with a solemn bow, and though she could not hear a word
of it, she felt as if hearing it all, and saw in the motion of his lips the words “apology,”
“Hunsford,” and “Lady Catherine de Bourgh.”
It vexed her to see him expose himself to such a man.
Mr. Darcy was eyeing him with unrestrained wonder; and when at last Mr. Collins allowed
him to speak, replied with an air of distant civility.
Mr. Collins, however, was not discouraged from speaking again, and Mr. Darcy’s contempt
seemed abundantly increasing with the length of his second speech; and at the end of it
he only made him a slight bow, and moved another way: Mr. Collins then returned to Elizabeth.
“I have no reason, I assure you,” said he, “to be dissatisfied with my reception.
Mr. Darcy seemed much pleased with the attention.
He answered me with the utmost civility, and even paid me the compliment of saying, that
he was so well convinced of Lady Catherine’s discernment as to be certain she could never
bestow a favour unworthily.
It was really a very handsome thought.
Upon the whole, I am much pleased with him.”
As Elizabeth had no longer any interest of her own to pursue, she turned her attention
almost entirely on her sister and Mr. Bingley; and the train of agreeable reflections which
her observations gave birth to made her perhaps almost as happy as Jane.
She saw her in idea settled in that very house, in all the felicity which a marriage of true
affection could bestow; and she felt capable, under such circumstances, of endeavouring
even to like Bingley’s two sisters.
Her mother’s thoughts she plainly saw were bent the same way, and she determined not
to venture near her, lest she might hear too much.
When they sat down to supper, therefore, she considered it a most unlucky perverseness
which placed them within one of each other; and deeply was she vexed to find that her
mother was talking to that one person (Lady Lucas) freely, openly, and of nothing else
but of her expectation that Jane would be soon married to Mr. Bingley.
It was an animating subject, and Mrs. Bennet seemed incapable of fatigue while enumerating
the advantages of the match.
His being such a charming young man, and so rich, and living but three miles from them,
were the first points of self-gratulation; and then it was such a comfort to think how
fond the two sisters were of Jane, and to be certain that they must desire the connection
as much as she could do.
It was, moreover, such a promising thing for her younger daughters, as Jane’s marrying
so greatly must throw them in the way of other rich men; and, lastly, it was so pleasant
at her time of life to be able to consign her single daughters to the care of their
sister, that she might not be obliged to go into company more than she liked.
It was necessary to make this circumstance a matter of pleasure, because on such occasions
it is the etiquette; but no one was less likely than Mrs. Bennet to find comfort in staying
at home at any period of her life.
She concluded with many good wishes that Lady Lucas might soon be equally fortunate, though
evidently and triumphantly believing there was no chance of it.
In vain did Elizabeth endeavour to check the rapidity of her mother’s words, or persuade
her to describe her felicity in a less audible whisper; for to her inexpressible vexation
she could perceive that the chief of it was overheard by Mr. Darcy, who sat opposite to
them.
Her mother only scolded her for being nonsensical.
“What is Mr. Darcy to me, pray, that I should be afraid of him?
I am sure we owe him no such particular civility as to be obliged to say nothing he may not
like to hear.”
“For heaven’s sake, madam, speak lower.
What advantage can it be to you to offend Mr. Darcy?
You will never recommend yourself to his friend by so doing.”
Nothing that she could say, however, had any influence.
Her mother would talk of her views in the same intelligible tone.
Elizabeth blushed and blushed again with shame and vexation.
She could not help frequently glancing her eye at Mr. Darcy, though every glance convinced
her of what she dreaded; for though he was not always looking at her mother, she was
convinced that his attention was invariably fixed by her.
The expression of his face changed gradually from indignant contempt to a composed and
steady gravity.
At length, however, Mrs. Bennet had no more to say; and Lady Lucas, who had been long
yawning at the repetition of delights which she saw no likelihood of sharing, was left
to the comforts of cold ham and chicken.
Elizabeth now began to revive.
But not long was the interval of tranquillity; for when supper was over, singing was talked
of, and she had the mortification of seeing Mary, after very little entreaty, preparing
to oblige the company.
By many significant looks and silent entreaties did she endeavour to prevent such a proof
of complaisance,—but in vain; Mary would not understand them; such an opportunity of
exhibiting was delightful to her, and she began her song.
Elizabeth’s eyes were fixed on her, with most painful sensations; and she watched her
progress through the several stanzas with an impatience which was very ill rewarded
at their close; for Mary, on receiving amongst the thanks of the table the hint of a hope
that she might be prevailed on to favour them again, after the pause of half a minute began
another.
Mary’s powers were by no means fitted for such a display; her voice was weak, and her
manner affected.
Elizabeth was in agonies.
She looked at Jane to see how she bore it; but Jane was very composedly talking to Bingley.
She looked at his two sisters, and saw them making signs of derision at each other, and
at Darcy, who continued, however, impenetrably grave.
She looked at her father to entreat his interference, lest Mary should be singing all night.
He took the hint, and, when Mary had finished her second song, said aloud,—
“That will do extremely well, child.
You have delighted us long enough.
Let the other young ladies have time to exhibit.”
Mary, though pretending not to hear, was somewhat disconcerted; and Elizabeth, sorry for her,
and sorry for her father’s speech, was afraid her anxiety had done no good.
Others of the party were now applied to.
“If I,” said Mr. Collins, “were so fortunate as to be able to sing, I should have great
pleasure, I am sure, in obliging the company with an air; for I consider music as a very
innocent diversion, and perfectly compatible with the profession of a clergyman.
I do not mean, however, to assert that we can be justified in devoting too much of our
time to music, for there are certainly other things to be attended to.
The rector of a parish has much to do.
In the first place, he must make such an agreement for tithes as may be beneficial to himself
and not offensive to his patron.
He must write his own sermons; and the time that remains will not be too much for his
parish duties, and the care and improvement of his dwelling, which he cannot be excused
from making as comfortable as possible.
And I do not think it of light importance that he should have attentive and conciliatory
manners towards everybody, especially towards those to whom he owes his preferment.
I cannot acquit him of that duty; nor could I think well of the man who should omit an
occasion of testifying his respect towards anybody connected with the family.”
And with a bow to Mr. Darcy, he concluded his speech, which had been spoken so loud
as to be heard by half the room.
Many stared—many smiled; but no one looked more amused than Mr. Bennet himself, while
his wife seriously commended Mr. Collins for having spoken so sensibly, and observed, in
a half-whisper to Lady Lucas, that he was a remarkably clever, good kind of young man.
To Elizabeth it appeared, that had her family made an agreement to expose themselves as
much as they could during the evening, it would have been impossible for them to play
their parts with more spirit, or finer success; and happy did she think it for Bingley and
her sister that some of the exhibition had escaped his notice, and that his feelings
were not of a sort to be much distressed by the folly which he must have witnessed.
That his two sisters and Mr. Darcy, however, should have such an opportunity of ridiculing
her relations was bad enough; and she could not determine whether the silent contempt
of the gentleman, or the insolent smiles of the ladies, were more intolerable.
The rest of the evening brought her little amusement.
She was teased by Mr. Collins, who continued most perseveringly by her side; and though
he could not prevail with her to dance with him again, put it out of her power to dance
with others.
In vain did she entreat him to stand up with somebody else, and offered to introduce him
to any young lady in the room.
He assured her that, as to dancing, he was perfectly indifferent to it; that his chief
object was, by delicate attentions, to recommend himself to her; and that he should therefore
make a point of remaining close to her the whole evening.
There was no arguing upon such a project.
She owed her greatest relief to her friend Miss Lucas, who often joined them, and good-naturedly
engaged Mr. Collins’s conversation to herself.
She was at least free from the offence of Mr. Darcy’s further notice: though often
standing within a very short distance of her, quite disengaged, he never came near enough
to speak.
She felt it to be the probable consequence of her allusions to Mr. Wickham, and rejoiced
in it.
The Longbourn party were the last of all the company to depart; and by a manœuvre of Mrs.
Bennet had to wait for their carriage a quarter of an hour after everybody else was gone,
which gave them time to see how heartily they were wished away by some of the family.
Mrs. Hurst and her sister scarcely opened their mouths except to complain of fatigue,
and were evidently impatient to have the house to themselves.
They repulsed every attempt of Mrs. Bennet at conversation, and, by so doing, threw a
languor over the whole party, which was very little relieved by the long speeches of Mr.
Collins, who was complimenting Mr. Bingley and his sisters on the elegance of their entertainment,
and the hospitality and politeness which had marked their behaviour to their guests.
Darcy said nothing at all.
Mr. Bennet, in equal silence, was enjoying the scene.
Mr. Bingley and Jane were standing together a little detached from the rest, and talked
only to each other.
Elizabeth preserved as steady a silence as either Mrs. Hurst or Miss Bingley; and even
Lydia was too much fatigued to utter more than the occasional exclamation of “Lord,
how tired I am!”
accompanied by a violent yawn.
When at length they arose to take leave, Mrs. Bennet was most pressingly civil in her hope
of seeing the whole family soon at Longbourn; and addressed herself particularly to Mr.
Bingley, to assure him how happy he would make them, by eating a family dinner with
them at any time, without the ceremony of a formal invitation.
Bingley was all grateful pleasure; and he readily engaged for taking the earliest opportunity
of waiting on her after his return from London, whither he was obliged to go the next day
for a short time.
Mrs. Bennet was perfectly satisfied; and quitted the house under the delightful persuasion
that, allowing for the necessary preparations of settlements, new carriages, and wedding
clothes, she should undoubtedly see her daughter settled at Netherfield in the course of three
or four months.
Of having another daughter married to Mr. Collins she thought with equal certainty,
and with considerable, though not equal, pleasure.
Elizabeth was the least dear to her of all her children; and though the man and the match
were quite good enough for her, the worth of each was eclipsed by Mr. Bingley and Netherfield.